Letters to David Hammond, 1968-2005
Emory University
Letters to David Hammond, 1968-2005
Heaney, Seamus, 1939-
Manuscript Collection No. 1019
1.75 linear ft. (4 boxes)
Letters from Irish poet Seamus Heaney to David and Eileen Hammond, as well as some photographs, printed material, and literary manuscripts.
Emory University Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library
Source
Purchase, 2006.
Restrictions on Access
Special restrictions apply: Letters by Seamus Heaney are closed to researchers.
Biographical Note
Seamus Heaney was born on April 13, 1939, the eldest child of nine born to a farming family in County Derry, Northern Ireland. He won a scholarship to St Columb's College, Derry, beginning an academic career that would lead, through Queen's University Belfast, where his first books of poems were written, to positions including Boylston Professor of Rhetoric and Oratory at Harvard and the Oxford Professor of Poetry. Among his many awards are the Nobel Prize for Literature 1995 and the Whitbread prize in 1987, 1996 and 1999. He was made a Commandeur de L'Ordre des Arts et Lettres in 1996.
David Hammond, folk singer, radio and film producer, was born in Belfast, Northern Ireland in 1928. Beginning in the 1950s, Hammond worked for the British Broadcasting Corporation Northern Ireland (BBC NI) as both a broadcaster and a film-maker. Hammond, along with Seamus Heaney, Tom Paulin and Brian Friel, served as directors when the Field Day Theatre was established in 1980. In 1986, Hammond formed Flying Fox Films, an independent company based in Belfast, which is primarily concerned with the production of television documentaries about Irish history, literature and culture.
Hammond and Heaney collaborated on a number of film and radio projects for the BBC NI, including "Something to Write Home About," formerly "The Sluggan." Hammond directed "Something to Write Home About," a television documentary produced by Fox Films about Seamus Heaney which was aired by the BBC NI in 1998.
Scope and Content Note
The collection primarily consists of letters from Seamus Heaney to David and Eileen Hammond from 1968-2005. There are approximately 50 letters and 250 postcards (a favorite form of correspondence for Heaney) from Heaney during his affiliations with the University of California, Berkeley and Harvard University, and while traveling in England and abroad. The collection also includes photographs, printed material, and literary manuscripts. The literary manuscripts include holograph drafts, corrected typescripts, and faxes or photocopies of early typescripts of published and unpublished poems, prose writings, and radio and film scripts. The draft scripts include "Something to Write Home About" and a subsequent draft text intended for publication.
Arrangement Note
Arranged by record type.
Related Materials in This Repository
Seamus Heaney collection and Seamus Heaney papers
Selected Search Terms
Topical Terms
English poetry--Irish authors.; Poets, Irish--20th century.
Form/Genre Terms
Manuscripts.; Photographs.
Container List
- Correspondence: Seamus Heaney to David and Eileen Hammond [RESTRICTED]
- 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 1970-1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- 1980-1989 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- 1990-1999 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- 2000-2005 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Collected Poems: Door into the Dark (1969)
- "Victorian Guitar," holograph draft, [1967] (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Collected Poems: No Man's Land [variant title: Wintering Out (1972)], carbon copy of early draft
- Title page and dedication, typescripts (Box 2, Folder 2)
- "Anahorish" and "Broagh," original typescript with revision (Box 2, Folder 3)
- "Aubade," [variant title: "Summer Home"], typescript (Box 2, Folder 4)
- "Augury," typescript (Box 2, Folder 5)
- "Bathing," typescript [variant title: "Summer Home"] (Box 2, Folder 6)
- "Bye-Child," typescript (Box 2, Folder 7)
- "Community Relations," typescript [variant title: "The Other Side"] (Box 2, Folder 8)
- "Dawn," typescript (Box 2, Folder 9)
- "Diptych: Offerings," typescript (Box 2, Folder 10)
- "Fireside," typescript (Box 2, Folder 11)
- "First Calf," typescript (Box 2, Folder 12)
- "Gifts of Rain," typescript (Box 2, Folder 13)
- "Good-night," typescript (Box 2, Folder 14)
- "Hawthorns," typescript (Box 2, Folder 15)
- "Home," typescript (Box 2, Folder 16)
- "Icon," typescript (Box 2, Folder 17)
- "The Last Mummer," typescript (Box 2, Folder 18)
- "Limbo," typescript (Box 2, Folder 19)
- "Linen Town," typescript (Box 2, Folder 20)
- "Maighdean Mara," typescript (Box 2, Folder 21)
- "May," typescript with revision (Box 2, Folder 22)
- "Midnight," typescript (Box 2, Folder 23)
- "Mother of the Groom," typescript (Box 2, Folder 24)
- "A Northern Hoard," typescript includes "Roots," " No Man's Land," "Stump," "No Sanctuary," and "Tinder" (Box 2, Folder 25)
- "Serenades," typescript (Box 2, Folder 26)
- "Servant Boy," typescript (Box 2, Folder 27)
- "Shore Woman," typescript with revision (Box 2, Folder 28)
- "The Smell," typescript (Box 2, Folder 29)
- "The Snare," typescript (Box 2, Folder 30)
- "Spile," typescript (Box 2, Folder 31)
- "The Tollund Man," typescript (Box 2, Folder 32)
- "Veteran's Dream," typescript (Box 2, Folder 33)
- "Wedding Day," typescript (Box 2, Folder 34)
- "Westering," typescripts (Box 2, Folder 35)
- "A Winter's Tale," typescript (Box 2, Folder 36)
- "The Wool Trade," typescript with revision (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Collected Poems: North (1975)
- "Exposure," typescript, signed by Seamus Heaney, December 18, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- "The Seed-Cutters," typescript with revision (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Collected Poems: Field Work (1979), photocopies and carbon copies of early drafts
- "An Afterwards," typescript (Box 2, Folder 40)
- "The Badgers," typescripts (Box 2, Folder 41)
- "Casualty," typescripts (Box 2, Folder 42)
- "A Dream of Jealousy," typescript (Box 2, Folder 43)
- "A Drink of Water," typescript (Box 2, Folder 44)
- "Elegy," typescripts (Box 2, Folder 45)
- "Field Work," typescripts (missing section III) (Box 2, Folder 46)
- "Glanmore Sonnets," typescripts (Box 2, Folder 47)
- "The Guttural Muse," typescript (Box 2, Folder 48)
- "High Summer," typescript (Box 2, Folder 49)
- "Homecomings," typescript (Box 2, Folder 50)
- "In Memoriam Francis Ledwidge," typescript (Box 2, Folder 51)
- "In Memoriam Sean O'Riada," typescript (Box 2, Folder 52)
- "Leavings," typescript (Box 2, Folder 53)
- "The Otter," typescript (Box 2, Folder 54)
- "Oysters," typescript (Box 2, Folder 55)
- "Polder," typescript (Box 2, Folder 56)
- "A Postcard from North Antrim," typescripts (Box 2, Folder 57)
- "September Song," typescript (Box 2, Folder 58)
- "The Seals," [variant title: "The Singer's House"] original typescript with inscription to David and Eileen by Heaney, August 15, 1976; photocopied typescript of "The Singer's House" (Box 2, Folder 59)
- "The Skunk," typescript (Box 2, Folder 60)
- "Song," typescript (Box 2, Folder 61)
- "The Strand at Lough Beg," typescript (Box 2, Folder 62)
- "The Toome Road," typescript (Box 2, Folder 63)
- "Triptych," includes "After a Killing," "Sibyl," "Song of Erne," [variant title: "At the Water's Edge"], typescripts (Box 2, Folder 64)
- "Ugolino," typescripts (Box 2, Folder 65)
- "The Wood Road," typescript (Box 2, Folder 66)
- Collected Poems: An Open Letter (1983)
- Four photocopied early typescript drafts with revisions (Box 2, Folder 67)
- Collected Poems: Station Island (1984)
- "The Loaning," typescript with inscription to David Hammond and signed by Seamus Heaney, January 3, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 68)
- "Sandstone," typescript, signed by Heaney, June 8, 1983, [variant title "Sandstone Keepsake"] (Box 2, Folder 69)
- "An Ulster Twilight," typescript with note (Box 2, Folder 70)
- Collected Poems: The Cure at Troy: a Version of Sophocles' Philoctetes (1990)
- Early photocopied typescript draft with revisions (Box 2, Folder 71)
- Collected Poems: Seeing Things (1991), photocopies of early drafts
- "The Ash Plant," typescript with revisions (Box 2, Folder 72)
- "Casting and Gathering," typescript draft with revisions (Box 2, Folder 73)
- "Crossings," typescript with revisions [ Squarings (2003)] (Box 2, Folder 74)
- "Glanmore Revisited," typescript (Box 2, Folder 75)
- "The Journey Back," typescript (Box 2, Folder 76)
- "Lightenings," typescript with revisions (Box 2, Folder 77)
- "Man and Boy," typescripts (Box 2, Folder 78)
- ["Offings," typescript; variant titles "Settings" and "Squarings"] (Box 2, Folder 79)
- "A Pillowed Head," typescript with revisions (Box 2, Folder 80)
- "The Pitchfork," typescript (Box 2, Folder 81)
- "A Retrospect," typescript with revisions (Box 2, Folder 82)
- "A Royal Prospect," typescript (Box 2, Folder 83)
- "The Schoolbag," typescript (Box 2, Folder 84)
- "Seeing Things," typescript (ie, Claritas…) (Box 2, Folder 85)
- "The Settle Bed," typescript (Box 2, Folder 86)
- "The Sounds of Rain," typescript (Box 2, Folder 87)
- "Three Drawings" includes "The Point," "The Pulse," and "A Haul," photocopied typescripts (Box 2, Folder 88)
- "Three Quatrains," includes "1939," "Pussy Willows," "The Rescue," photocopied typescripts (Box 2, Folder 89)
- "Wheels within Wheels," typescript (Box 2, Folder 90)
- Collected Poems: The Spirit Level (1996), photocopies of original draft
- Title page, table of contents, and acknowledgements together with letter from Roxann Brown to David Hammond, 28 June 1995, typescripts (Box 3, Folder 1)
- "An Architect," typescript (Box 3, Folder 2)
- "A Brigid's Girdle," typescript (Box 3, Folder 3)
- "At Banagher," typescript (Box 3, Folder 4)
- "The Butter-Print," typescript (Box 3, Folder 5)
- "A Call," typescript (Box 3, Folder 6)
- "Clang and Contour," typescript (Box 3, Folder 7)
- "The Clay Pipes," typescript (Box 3, Folder 8)
- "Damson," typescript (Box 3, Folder 9)
- "A Dog Was Crying To-Night in Wicklow Also," typescript (Box 3, Folder 10)
- "To a Dutch Potter in Ireland," typescript (Box 3, Folder 11)
- "The Errand," typescript (Box 3, Folder 12)
- "The Flight Path," typescript (Box 3, Folder 13)
- "Four Finger Exercise: The Thimble," typescript (Box 3, Folder 14)
- "The Gravel Walks," typescript (Box 3, Folder 15)
- "An Invocation," typescript (Box 3, Folder 16)
- "Keeping Going," typescript (Box 3, Folder 17)
- "Mint," typescript (Box 3, Folder 18)
- "Mycenae Lookout," typescript (Box 3, Folder 19)
- "The Poet's Chair," typescript (Box 3, Folder 20)
- "Postscript," typescript (Box 3, Folder 21)
- "The Rain Stick," typescript (Box 3, Folder 22)
- "Remembered Columns," typescript (Box 3, Folder 23)
- "Saint Kevin and the Blackbird," typescript (Box 3, Folder 24)
- "The Sharping Stone," typescript (Box 3, Folder 25)
- "A Sofa in the Forties," typescript (Box 3, Folder 26)
- "Something Else," typescript (Box 3, Folder 27)
- "The Swing," typescript (Box 3, Folder 28)
- "Tollund," typescript (Box 3, Folder 29)
- "A Transgression," typescript (Box 3, Folder 30)
- "Two Lorries," typescript (Box 3, Folder 31)
- "Two Stick Drawings," typescript (Box 3, Folder 32)
- "The Walk," typescript (Box 3, Folder 33)
- "Weighing In," typescript (Box 3, Folder 34)
- "At the Wellhead," typescript (Box 3, Folder 35)
- "Whitby-sur-Moyola," typescript (Box 3, Folder 36)
- Collected Poems: The Door Stands Open: Czeslaw Milosz, 1911-2004 (2005)
- "What Passed at Colonus," with revision (Box 3, Folder 37)
- Uncollected Poems
- "In Bellaghy Graveyard," typescript, facsimile (Box 3, Folder 38)
- "A Cart for Edward Gallagher," photocopy from unidentified published source (Box 3, Folder 39)
- "From Chekov's Donegal Journal," carbon typescript with handwritten inscription to David Hammond and Eileen, July 1981 (Box 3, Folder 40)
- "Dialogues," carbon typescript with handwritten note by Seamus Heaney (Box 3, Folder 41)
- "A Dream of Solstice," typescript facsimile, midwinter at Newgrange, 1999; [first published in The Kenyon Review, Winter 2001] (Box 3, Folder 42)
- "Dream of the Trenches," with handwritten note by David Hammond, clipping from unidentified published source (Box 3, Folder 43)
- "Frame of Mind," typescript (Box 3, Folder 44)
- "Going Back," original typescript with note to David Hammond signed by Seamus Heaney, 26 July 1982 (Box 3, Folder 45)
- "The Lesson," photocopied typescript with handwritten inscription to David Hammond, 25 February 1998, two copies (Box 3, Folder 46)
- "Postcards," handwritten on verso of calendar for month of December 1984 (Box 3, Folder 47)
- "The Professor of Poetry's After-Dinner Remarks Ventriloquized in the Style of Percy French's ‘The Queen's After-Dinner Speech," typescript signed by Seamus Heaney, May 18, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 48)
- "A Shuttle for Big D., 5 October 1993," a birthday poem for David Hammond, holograph with inscription by Seamus Heaney (Box 3, Folder 49)
- Un-titled poem with first line "There was a young man from Belfast," photocopied typescript, 2 copies (Box 3, Folder 50)
- Prose
- Address (includes poem) for launch of "Campaign for Queens", photocopied typescript, November 8, 2001; a campaign to provide funding for new capital, academic, and community initiatives at Queens University of Belfast (Box 3, Folder 51)
- Biographical note for Seamus Heaney, photocopied typescript, [1984] (Box 3, Folder 52)
- "Explorations," typescripts with Seamus Heaney's handwritten notes on broadcasts together with typing instructions from David Hammond to [Marie], 9 September 1973; a series of ten BBC radio broadcasts on literary themes with introductions by Heaney, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 53)
- The Government of the Tongue, original draft, typescript introduction with note to David Hammond, October 1, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 54)
- Lord of the Flies, holograph teaching notes (Box 3, Folder 55)
- "Mary Holland," typescript with revisions; Seamus Heaney's eulogy at Holland's funeral, June 7, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 56)
- Obituary for Stewart Parker by Seamus Heaney, typescript photocopy with revisions, November 2 1988 (Box 3, Folder 57)
- The People of the Sea: Celtic Tales of the Seal Folk by David Thomson (2001): Introduction by Seamus Heaney, facsimile typescript with revisions (Box 3, Folder 58)
- Seamus Heaney's eulogy at the funeral of Paddy Falloon, June 2003, typescript (Box 3, Folder 59)
- "The Singer's House," Seamus Heaney's review of record by David Hammond and Donal Lunny, typescript with revisions, May Day 1978 (Box 3, Folder 60)
- A Way of Life like Any Other by Darcy O'Brien (2001): Introduction by Seamus Heaney, facsimile typescript (Box 3, Folder 61)
- Scripts
- Boyne Valley radio program, handwritten notes and typescript, undated (Box 3, Folder 62)
- "I am of Irlande," original first draft, typed radio script with revisions, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 63)
- "Islandman," handwritten [radio script?] with typed insertions, undated (Box 3, Folder 64)
- "Something to Write Home About," formerly " The Sluggan," television film script and proposal, drafts, notes, correspondence, 1996-2002 (Box 3, Folder 65)
- "Something to Write Home About," first and second drafts revised text prepared for publication by David Hammond, typescript, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 66)
- "Ulster in Focus: The Loughsiders," typed film script, 1972, narrated by Seamus Heaney and produced by David Hammond (Box 3, Folder 67)
- Photographs
- Seamus Heaney, with others including children, Christmas, 1971, three color photographs (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Seamus Heaney, with others, Christmas, 1972, two black and white photographs (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Seamus Heaney visiting Hugh MacDiarmid and his wife Zelda with D.H. and Trevor Royle, [Southern Uplands] near [Galashiels], 1977, seven black and white photographs (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Seamus Heaney after the release of the record The Singer's House, 1978, three black and white photographs (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Seamus Heaney, and others filming in the Boyne Valley at Newgrange, autumn 1979, five color photographs (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Seamus Heaney, after a reading in Syracuse, NY while staying with Dan Casey, 1979, five black and white photographs (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Seamus Heaney, visiting farm with children, [1970s], five black and white photographs; photographer: Jim Bennett (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Seamus Heaney and others at Derek Hill's Studio, McPheeter's Farm near [Garthas], Co. Donegal; Faber had commissioned Derek Hill to paint a portrait of Seamus for his 50th birthday, 1989, four color photographs (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Seamus Heaney and David Hammond visiting Master McGrath monument near [Dungarran,] Co. Waterford, 1993, eight color photographs (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Seamus Heaney's Nobel Prize homecoming celebration with family and friends, Roley's Bistro, Dublin, November, 1995, 26 color photographs (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Mechanical harvesting of a peat bog, Ireland, undated, three black and white photographs; photographers: Rex Roberts Studios Ltd. and Deegan Photo Ltd., Dublin (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Printed material
- "In Their Element: a Programme of Poetry by Seamus Heaney & Derek Mahon," brochure for reading tour, [1977] (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Published obituaries from various newspapers including one in Polish for the Polish poet Czeslaw Milosz, August 2004 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Cartoon from unknown published source with caption in [Hammond’s] hand, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)